Gothenburg Research Infrastructure in Digital Humanities

University of Gothenburg ☑ matteo.tomasini@lir.gu.se Website: mtomasini.github.io Citizenship: Switzerland Birthdate: 21 Nov 1989



Matteo Tomasini

Research engineer

Summary

I am an enthusiastic research software engineer working in archaeology and digital humanities. My main interest is to support researchers in developing new computational tools, data pipelines and scientific visualizations. I have a keen eye for using the right methods for each problem at hand. My toolbox is suited for agent-based modelling, full-stack development, data analysis, statistical and mathematical modelling, and more. I am also involved in the dissemination of good programming practices in academia, as well as in the development of the careers of research software engineers in the Nordics.

Skills

Agent-based modelling, programming, (Python, R, C++, Matlab), I developed various population- and individual-based simulations to address questions in population genetics and climatology. I am active developer of a seafaring simulator.

Full-stack development, (Django, PostgreSQL; Vue; Sphinx), I contribute to the development, deployment and maintenance of the web platforms currently in use at my department.

Statistical analysis, (Python, R, Stan), I performed statistical analysis on simulations outputs and datasets using different methodologies, including Bayesian inference and machine learning. I further worked towards the development of a statistical method to extract information from genomic datasets. I also taught applied biostatistics to master students.

Scientific writing, (LATEX, Word), I wrote several papers exposing the research results from my team, and published them in international peer-reviewed journals.

Leadership and management, I am the assigned manager for several projects involving scientific visualization. I also organize seminars and conferences for the Nordic RSE association. In the past, I led and managed the logistics of an artillery battery during military service in Switzerland.

Mathematical and numerical modelling, (Wolfram Mathematica), I worked on several mathematical models to study selected questions in population genetics and climatology.

Scientific dissemination, I contributed during 10 years to the growth of one of the largest Facebook pages about popular science in Italian.

Experience

Current employment

Nov 2022 - Present Research engineer, Gothenburg Research Infrastructure in Digital Humanities, Göteborgs Universitet, Sweden

> I develop and maintain agent-based simulations to study seafaring in the Bronze Age. I am further involved in the development of research web platforms in digital humanities.

Feb 2023 – Present Application expert, InfraVis, Sweden

I develop and manage different products for external users within the Swedish national infrastructure for scientific visualization, InfraVis (10% employment).

Past employment

Mar 2021 – Oct 2022 **Postdoctoral research fellow**, Department of Marine Sciences, Göteborgs Universitet, Sweden

I modelled evolutionary mechanisms leading to the establishment of species' distributions in the Baltic Sea, using Python, C++ and Matlab.

Sep 2019 – Dec 2020 **Postdoctoral research associate**, Department of Integrative Biology, Michigan State University, United States of America

I worked on developing a Bayesian statistical method to harness genetic information for the inference of the demographic history of a species.

Feb 2015 – Jun 2019 **PhD student**, *Interfaculty Bioinformatics Unit, Universität Bern, Switzerland*I developed mathematical models and simulations in Python to study the rapid adaptation of species at risk of extinction in a spatially structured model.

Teaching

Sep 2022 Course co-leader, Software testing, CodeRefinery

Co-teaching a course about automated testing during the yearly CodeRefinery workshop.

Sep 2017 – Jun 2019 **Substitute lecturer**, *Applied Biostatistics I and II*, Universität Bern Substitution of main lecturer in case of absence.

Sep 2015 – Jun 2019 **Teaching assistant**, *Applied Biostatistics I and II*, Universität Bern Management of exercise sessions and support for MSc students, correction of exercise sheets.

Sep 2015, 2016, 2017 **Teaching assistant**, *Introduction to R*, Universität Bern and 2018 Teaching assistant during a 5 days introductory course to the R language.

Education

Feb 2015 – Jun 2019 **PhD studies in ecology & evolution**, *Universität Bern, Switzerland*, Supervisors: Dr. S. Peischl and Prof. L. Excoffier

Relevant courses and workshops: best practices in programming, introduction to Markov models, machine learning. Thesis topic: theoretical population genetics.

Sep 2012 – Oct 2014 **MSc in physics (orientation theoretical physics)**, *Université de Genève, Switzerland*

Thesis topic: theoretical climatology.

Sep 2009 – Aug 2012 BSc in physics, Université de Genève, Switzerland

Sep 2004 – Jun 2008 **Swiss Matura (classical curriculum)**, *Liceo di Locarno, Switzerland* Relevant courses: ancient Greek, Latin.

Academic achievments and activities

Software and web applications

- 2. J. Westin, T. Bridge, **M. Tomasini**, *Saint Sophia's Inscriptions*, v.1.0 GRIDH. https://saintsophia.dh.gu.se/
- 1. J. Westin, T. Bridge, **M. Tomasini**, *Etruscan Chamber Tombs*, v.1.0 GRIDH. https://etruscan.dh.gu.se/

Peer-reviewed publications

- 4. J. Westin, T. Bridge, **M. Tomasini** (2024), *From the Arctics to Antarctica A multimodular visualisation of data*, Proceedings of the Huminfra Conference (HiC 2024), 135 140
- 3. **M. Tomasini**, S. Peischl, (2022), *The role of spatial structure in multi-deme models of evolutionary rescue*, Journal of Evolutionary Biology, 35(7), 986 1001
- 2. **M. Tomasini**, S. Peischl, (2020), When does gene flow facilitate evolutionary rescue?, Evolution, 74(8), 1640 1653

1. **M. Tomasini**, S. Peischl, (2018), *Establishment of locally adapted mutations under divergent selection*, Genetics, 209(3), 885 – 895

Pre-prints

- J. Rieder, M. Jahnke, ..., M. Tomasini, F. A. M. Volckaert (2024), Seascape genomics: assisting marine biodiversity management by combining genetic knowledge with environmental and ecological information, EcoEvoRxiv, https://doi.org/10.32942/X2KW30 – submitted
- 1a. **M. Tomasini**, M. Eriksson, K. Johannesson, M. Rafajlović (2022), *Shallow environmental gradients can cause range margins to form*, bioRxiv, https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.03.19.484973

Grants

- 9500 SEK (~866€) Kungliga Vetenskaps- och Vitterhets-Samhället i Göteborg (KVVS) Stipendium 2022
 - 750€ International Council for the Exploration of the Sea (ICES) Early Career Scientist funding, Baltic Sea Science Congress 2021
- Rejected with Seal of *The evolution of marine species in continuous space*, Marie Skłodowska-Curie Actions Excellence Individual Fellowship 2020, Evaluation Score: 90.40%

Selected oral contributions

- Dec 2024 MetaPypulation: Sieving and shifting cultural traits across space, Theoretical Archaeology Group, Bournemouth, UK
- Jan 2024 From the Arctics to Antarctica A multimodular visualisation of data, Huminfra Conference, Gothenburg, Sweden
- Oct 2022 Fight or flight? The role of adaptation in shaping future species' distributions in light of climate change (featured session), YOUMARES 13, Berlin, Germany
- Aug 2022 How do species ranges respond to the effects of counteracting environmental gradients?, European Society for Evolutionary Biology Congress 2022, Prague, Czech Republic

Committees and academic roles

Aug 2024 – present Ambassador, CodeRefinery

Oct 2022 - present Board chair, Nordic Research Software Engineers association

Oct 2021 – Feb 2023 Steering committee, Linnaeus Centre for Marine Evolutionary Biology, University of Gothenburg

Memberships

May 2022 – present Nordic Research Software Engineers association

Apr 2021 - present Linnaeus Centre for Marine Evolutionary Biology, University of Gothenburg

Mar 2015 - Jul 2019 Swiss Institute of Bioinformatics

Unpaid research experience

- Sep 2013 Oct 2014 **MSc thesis**, Effect of snow covering and ocean mixed layer on the irreversibility of sea ice retreat, Institut des Sciences de l'Environnement, Université de Genève, Supervisors: Dr. M. Brunetti and Dr. S. Marshall
 - Feb 2012 **BSc short thesis**, *Measures of polarization of the solar light around the Balmer Jump*, Istituto Ricerche Solari Locarno and Université de Genève, Supervisors: Dr. M. Bianda and Dr. M. Audard

Miscellaneous

Languages

written / spoken Italian Native language

written / spoken French Full professional working proficiency written / spoken English Full professional working proficiency

spoken German Limited working proficiency

written / spoken Swedish Base proficiency (Nationella prov i SFI, kurs C)

Other activities

Mar 2012 - Mar 2022 Co-admin, Meccanica Quantistica: gruppo serio

Co-administrator and moderator of the largest Facebook page of quantum physics dissemi-

nation in Italian language (\sim 34'000 subscribers).

Aug 2009 - Apr 2019 Battery Sergeant Major, Swiss Armed Forces

> I was responsible for logistics in an artillery battery – in particular personnel, equipment, ammunition, health service and barracks administration - during the yearly one month

service.

Nov 2015 - Jun 2018 Head of refereeing, Swiss Tchoukball

> Head of the refereeing commission and member of the executive committee of the Swiss federation of tchoukball; I developed refereeing in the sport as well as worked on referees'

formation.

Leisure activities

Regular practice of triathlon (2006-2020) and trail running (since 2021), with Endurance sports

completion of several races up to half-ironman distance.

Regular practice of visual astronomy as well as astronomy sketching since 2023. Visual astronomy

Regular practice of piano playing since 1997; self-taught guitar player; I sang in 3

choirs between 2006 and 2015.